Register of the Susan Weissman Radio Broadcast Interviews
Hoover Institution Archives
- 1992
  - Cold War Dilemma in U.S. (Weissman interviews James Petris, of the State University of New York at Binghamton, on the escalation of economic contradictions in the U.S. following the demise of the USSR and the end of the Cold War), 29 October 1992 (Box 5)
  - Russian Economics Askew (Weissman interviews H. Ticktin, Institute of Soviet and European Studies at the University of Glasgow, on the economic shambles left by decades of Stalinism), 5 November 1992 (Box 5)
  - The Serbian Peace Movement in Yugoslavia (F. Filipovich of "B-92" (Belgrade 92) radio station is interviewed by Weissman on the Serbian peace efforts in Yugoslavia. Translation by Vera Matic), 12 November 1992 (Box 5)
  - The New World Disorder, (Weissman interviews Professor Michael Cox, Queens University, Belfast, Northern Ireland, on world-wide disorder in the wake of the end of the cold war.), 10 December 1992 (Box 5)
  - N. Preobrajensky Article (Weissman reads an article entitled "The Disarray of Social Forces and Political Perspectives for the TYE Workers' Movement in the Ex-USSR" written by N. Preobrajensky, grandson of E.A. Preobrajensky, a veteran Trotskyist executed by Stalin in 1937), 17 December 1992 (Box 5)
  - Third World Without Stalinism (Dr. James Petris, State University of New York at Binghamton discusses the impact on Third-world countries of the end of the USSR, the immediate and the long-term effects), 24 December 1992 (Box 5)
  - Economic Chaos in Ex-USSR (Weissman interviews Associate Professor of Politics, University California at Santa Cruz, Michael Urban, who just returned from Moscow), 31 December 1992 (Box 5)
- 1993
  - Racism and Anti-Racism in Europe (Weissman interviews Fahar Besherat, president of the International Organization of Iranian Emigrants in Europe, on racism and anti-racism in Europe), 7 January 1993 (Box 5)
  - Discussion on Early Years of CPUSA (James P. Cannon and the Early Years of American Communism is a new book compiled by Spartacist members Emily Turnbull, archivist of the Prometheus Press (the publishers) and James Robertson, director of the Prometheus Press), 4 February 1993 (Box 5)
  - Women in the New World Disorder (Weissman interviews Nanette Funk, who teaches philosophy at Brooklyn College in NY, and who co-edited a new book Gender Politics and Post-Communism: Reflections from East Europe and the Former Soviet Union, published by Rutledge), 11 March 1993 (Box 5)
  - Labor's Role in "Market Transition" (Vladimir Kondratov, a deputy of the Moscow City Council and an executive of the General Confederation of Trade Unions and Weissman discuss current problems of the transition with particular emphasis on the role of trade unions during the perplexing scene toward a "market" economy), 1 April 1993 (Box 5)
  - Economic Chaos in USSR (Weissman interviews H. Ticktin, Institute of Soviet and European Studies at the University of Glasgow, on the real meaning of April 1993 elections), 8 April 1993 (Box 5)
  - Russian and Greek Speeches at NYC Socialist Conference (Includes speeches by Aleksandr Buzgalin, Party of Labor in Russia, and Sabas Michael Matas, Gen. Secretary of the Greek Revolutionary Party), 22 April 1993 (Box 5)
  - The Russian Election Scene (In an article in The Village Voice the Los Angeles journalist Mark Cooper discusses the economic and political chaos he observed during a 10-day visit to the Moscow area during the Yeltsin Referendum period), 7 May 1993 (Box 5)
  - Chaos in Yeltsin's Moscow (Weissman interviews Mark Cooper on his experiences and conclusions after a visit to Moscow to observe the Yeltsin voting confusion), 14 May 1993 (Box 5)
  - Continued Chaos in Russia (Weissman interviews H. Ticktin, on the progression in the former USSR to chaos and economic anarchy as attempts are made to initiate a "market" economy), 21 May 1993 (Box 5)
  - Yugoslavia: Conflict Origins and Future (Betty Denich, faculty member of Harvard University, and Weissman discuss the origins of the continued strife in Yugoslavia), 28 May 1993 (Box 5)
  - The Continuing Crisis in Yugoslavia (Branca Magas, a Croatian nationalist and a former staff member of New Left Review of London and Weissman discuss the origins and continuing crisis in Yugoslavia), 4 June 1993 (Box 5)
  - End of Cold War Brings World-wide Chaos (Michael Cox, a lecturer at Queen's University at Belfast, Northern Ireland, and Weissman discuss the world-wide chaos, political, economic, and military (especially nuclear weapons) as the stabilizing era of the cold war evaporates), 18 June 1993 (Box 6)
  - Bread and Salt Movie Makers Interviewed (Irina Murav'eva and Gene Kallachia discuss the new Russian movie that deals with a return to what was once the USSR), 9 July 1993 (Box 6)
  - The Legacy of Chernobyl and Other Problems (Weissman interviews Volodymir Yarovivs'kii, chairman of the investigative commission exposing the cover-up of the 1986 Chernobyl disaster, a representative of the Kiev Parliamentaian District, and other high Ukrainian offices. Dr. Bohdan Futala translates), 16 July 1993 (Box 6)
  - A Horatio Alger Story from the Ex-USSR (Weissman interviews Valery Chudovsky, a true-to-life Russian businessman who, in Horatio Alger style, made it big), 23 July 1993 (Box 6)
  - The Cover-ups of Education (Clare Spark and Weissman discuss the cover-ups in the teaching of history and the paucity of genuine scholarship throughout the educational hierarchy), 30 July 1993 (Box 6)
  - Cold War Spy Exchanges (Weissman interviews Craig Whitney, European correspondent of the New York Times and author of the new book Spy Trader, tracing the colorful history of East German lawyer Wolfgang Vogel, who enjoyed the confidence of East and West in the Cold War. He negotiated some 34,000 transfers from East Germany to West Germany including the exchange of Gary Powers for Rudolph Abel and the exchange of Anatoly Shcharansky for spies from the eastern block), 20 August 1993 (Box 6)
  - Disorder in South Africa: Order in Israel? (By telephone from Scotland Weissman interviews H. Ticktin, on his recent trip to South Africa. He comments also on the background and meaning of the Israel-Arab peace accord), 10 September 1993 (Box 6)
  - What Next in the Near East? (Weissman and Ali Javadi, Dept. of History at the University of California at Los Angeles, discuss the impact of the just completed Pro-Israeli peace pact), 17 September 1993 (Box 6)
  - Yeltsin/Parliament Crisis in Russia (Weissman discusses the new Yeltsin-Parliament crisis with Marshall Coldman, Harvard Russian Research Center, and with H. Ticktin, by phone from Glasgow), 24 September 1993 (Box 6)
  - Yeltsin's October Crisis Continues (The Yeltsin-Parliament crisis continues. Weissman discusses it with David Mandel of the University of Montreal in Quebec, and with H. Ticktin, University of Glasgow), 1 October 1993 (Box 6)
  - Yeltsin Coup Seen by Three Experts (This is a 30 minute special broadcast on Sunday, October 3, on Yeltsin's coup. Weissman interviews Alexander Buscalin in Moscow and others, 3 October 1993 (Box 6)
  - Kagarlitsky on Meaning of Yeltsin Coup (On October 7, Weissman had an extended interview with Boris Kagarlitsky, a member of the Moscow City Council, on the Yeltsin "Neo-October" coup), 8 October 1993 (Box 6)
  - After the Coup: News from Russia (Weissman reads from various sources reactions to the October Yeltsin coup), 15 October 1993 (Box 6)
  - Important New Book: Molotov's Memoirs (Weissman interviews Albert Resis, Prof. History emeritus Northern Illinois University, on Molotov Remembers - Inside Kremlin Politics - Conversations with Felix Chuev, Based on extended interviews with Molotov), 22 October 1993 (Box 6)
  - Interview in Moscow with R. Clarke (Weissman interviews Clarke (an Australian journalist who has lived in Moscow for the past four years) in connection with an international conference supporting political freedom. Sound quality is very poor), 12 November 1993 (Box 6)
  - Elections No Answer to Russian Crisis (Weissman interviews by telephone Renfrey Clarke, correspondent of the Australian Green Left Weekly, on the chaos that continues under the Yeltsin's regime), 10 December 1993 (Box 6)
  - Rigged Elections No Russian Solution (Weissman interviews H. Ticktin on the Yeltsin elections.), 17 December 1993 (Box 6)
- 1994
  - KPFK Covers Chiapas, Mexico Uprising (Weissman and Clare Sparks discuss the content, causes, and economic background of anti-Semitism, fascism, and nationalism. On side B radio station KPFK updates the causes and status of the rebellion of peasants in Chiapas province, Mexico), 7 January 1994 (Box 6)
  - Russia Sinks Into Economic Morass (Weissman and Dr. H. Ticktin, agree that the efforts to bring "the market" to the ex-Soviet Union have proven to be a failure. It applies also to Poland and Eastern European countries), 28 January 1994 (Box 6)
  - Russia in Turmoil with Weissman, Scheer, and Cockburn (Russia in Turmoil was a program held in Los Angeles 4 February 1994. Featured speakers were Weissman, Robert Scheer, Alexander Cockburn, and Gloria Romero. This tape does not include question and answer period) (Box 6)
  - Russia in Turmoil Meeting (contd.) Program broadcast on Weissman's "Portraits" series, 11 February 1994 (Box 6)
  - Discussing Democracy (Weissman and Clare Spark discuss the meaning of democracy and the malaise of the left following proof of Stalin's crimes and the subsequent fall of the Soviet Union), 18 February 1994 (Box 6)
  - Russian "Reforms" Generate Chaos (Dr. Lynn Nelson, sociology professor, and Dr. Irina Kuzes, Dept. of Urban Planning, Moscow, and Visiting Professor at Virginia Commonwealth University, discuss the failure of radical reforms in the ex-USSR. Dr. Nelson is updating his book Property to the People: the Struggle for Economic Reform published by M.E. Sharpe), 25 March 1994 (Box 6)
  - Romania in Transition (Weissman and Dr. Thomas Kleininger, director of the Humanitas Publishing House of Bucharest, Romania, discuss the problems and pitfalls of the transition from a dictatorship to a "democratic market" economic system), 4 April 1994 (Box 6)
  - Democracy Fight in Ex-USSR (Weissman interviews Prof. Alexander Buzgalin, Moscow University, in the fight for democracy in the ex-USSR. He also gives an analysis of the contradictions in the failing attempt to convert, the ex-USSR to a capitalist "market" system. The first 5 minutes of the broadcast were missing), 8 April 1994 (Box 6)
  - Daniel Singer on Post-Stalin Socialism (Weissman interviews Singer, The Nation's correspondent in Europe, on the post-Stalin problems of socialist movements.), 15 April 1994 (Box 6)
  - The Future of Socialism UC/Berkeley (Singer, Paris based European correspondent for The Nation magazine, talks at Berkeley on the "Future of Socialism."), 1 May 1994 (Box 6)
  - USSR Archives Now Partially Opened (Weissman interviews Dr. Alexander Pantsov, a senior research fellow at the Russian Assn. of Political Scientists and a specialist in the Russian and Chinese Revolution Central (Russian) Party Archives. New insights into Lenin-Stalin-Trotsky relationships, and the development of Russian and Chinese national socialism are shown), 20 May 1994 (Box 6)
  - USSR Party Archives Show Stalin's Rise (Weissman interviews Dr. Alexander Pantsov), 20 May 1994 (Box 6)
  - Russian People Suffer as Economy Slides (Weissman interviews Dr. Robert Arnat, Caledonian University Department of Economics, Glasgow, on his recent revisit to Russia), 24 June 1994 (Box 6)
  - Marxism in US: A Retrospective (Weissman and Clare Spark conduct a wide-ranging informal retrospective on the past, present, and possible future development of a Marxist society in the USA), 1 July 1994 (Box 6)
  - Unrest and Crime in Russia (Weissman interviews Dr. H. Ticktin on the deepening chaos, economic degradation, great growth of crime, as the former Soviet Union attempts to establish a capitalist society, 8 July 1994 (Box 6)
  - Memories of U.S. Left (Tim Wohlforth, author of The Prophet's Children: Travels on the American Left and Weissman discuss their participation in the student movement of college leftists), 15 July 1994 (Box 6)
  - Early Evolution of U.S. Trotskyism (Weissman interviews Albert Glotzer, a.k.a. Albert Gates, on the early evolution of Trotyskyism from the point of view of a veteran who knew Trotsky in Turkish and French exile, and who was the official court reporter at the Dewey hearings in Coyoacan, Mexico. His book, Trotsky: Memoir and Critique details 60 years of his life in the American Trotskyist movement), 22 July 1994 (Box 6)
  - Dismantling Utopia (Weissman interviews Scott Shane, a reporter for The Baltimore Sun on his new book Dismantling Utopia in which he notes the almost complete breakdown in infrastructure, especially communications, imposed by bureaucracy), 29 July 1994 (Box 6)
  - Soviet Workers After Perestroika (Weissman interviews Donald Siltzer, senior lecturer in European Studies, Dept. of Sociology at the University of East London, the author of a trilogy of Soviet labor's response to a system imposed on them. The latest book, Soviet Workers and Collapse of Perestroika (Cambridge University Press) addresses Gorbachev Reforms 1986-1991), 2 September 1994 (Box 6)
  - Cuba's Dilemmas Today (Weissman interviewed Marc Cooper, an independent journalist based in Los Angeles, describing what he found in a two week visit to Cuba), 9 September 1994 (Box 6)
  - USSR and China's "Perestroikas" analyzed (Weissman and Dr. Yuri Ovchinnikov, a China specialist, visiting scholar at University of Southern California, a former member of Russian Academy of Sciences in Moscow and the Institute of Eastern Studies discuss and analyze the similarities and differences driving the changes in Russia and China today), 7 October 1994 (Box 6)
  - Belgrade, Ex-Yugoslavia, in Disarray (Florence Levinsohn, author, journalist, traveler, and Weissman discuss the new book, Belgrade - Among the Serbs), 14 October 1994 (Box 6)
  - A Reactionary World Seen by a Reporter (Weissman interviews journalist Mark Cooper, a reporter whose new book, Roll Over, Che Guevara, has just been published by Verso Press. Cooper feels Republican victory in U.S. is symbolic of the success of media and politicians to alienate the working class from voting and participating in radical politics), 11 November 1994 (Box 6)
  - Readings on Aftermath of U.S. Elections (Weissman reads editorial and other sources of opinions on the significance of the November 8 elections in the USA. Sources include Against the Current and The Nation), 25 November 1994 (Box 6)
  - Report on the First Trotsky Conference (Marilyn Vogt-Downey, who participated in the first conference on Trotsky held in Russia in about 70 years, reports on her impressions and significance of the conference. She is the editor of the new book USSR 1987 to 1992, Marxist Perspectives), 2 December 1994 (Box 6)
  - The Meaning of the Chechnia Revolt (Weissman and Dr. H. Ticktin discuss the reasons behind Russia's invasion of the former Soviet enclave Chechnia; they note the fact that there are oil interests there, that the invasion reflects the failure to establish a "market" economy), 23 December 1994 (Box 7)
- 1995
  - Chechnia: Yeltsin's Waterloo? (In a telephone conversation, Renfrey Clarke, the Moscow correspondent for the Australian Green Left Review, and Weissman discuss the catastrophe brewing in Chechnia), 6 January 1995 (Box 7)
  - Labor Leader Mazzochi Is Interviewed (Anthony Mazzochi, former vice-president and secretary-treasurer of the Oil, Chemical, and Atomic Workers International, and now its presidential assistant, is interviewed by Weissman. He holds that none of the current U.S. political parties offer any hope to American workers), 17 February 1995 (Box 7)
  - How Republicans "Steal" U.S. Elections (Marc Cooper, former news director at KPFK-FM Los Angeles, is interviewed by Dr. Suzan Weissman on how the directed misinformation of both major parties brought an alleged Republican "landslide" in U.S. elections), 24 February 1995 (Box 7)
  - Why Yeltsin Attacked Chechnia (Edward Walker, director for Soviet and Post-Soviet Studies at UC-Berkeley, and Weissman review the complex reasons why Russia's Yeltsin attacked Chechnia), 17 March 1995 (Box 7)
  - Republican Assault on Public TV, Radio (Nicholas Johnson, University of Iowa College of Law, former head of the Federal Communications Commission, Mark Lowenthal of "Project Censored," California State University Sonoma, and Paul Rosenberg of Committee to Save Public Media, join Weissman in discussing the major assault on all media and free speech under the aegis of Republican right and others such as the religious right), 24 March 1995 (Box 7)
  - Yeltsin's Chechnia Policy Probed (Weissman and Alexander Buzgalin, member of the Executive Committee of the Russian Party of Labor, discuss Yeltsin's unpopular Chechnia policy), 31 March 1995 (Box 7)
  - Russia's Turmoil (Weissman and Boris Kagarlitsky, author of books on the USSR and Russia and former member of the first Moscow City Council discuss the fluid political situation in Russia as Yeltsin is unable to solve economic problems, which gives rise to increasing dissent and growth of old and new parties), 7 April 1995 (Box 7)
  - Right Wing/Terrorist Resurgence (Weissman and H. Ticktin, editor of Critique, author of The Politics of Race, discuss the international rise of the right and of terrorism in a world of disorder), 21 April 1995 (Box 7)
  - Bombing No Stranger to U.S. History (Weissman and Clare Spark discuss the philosophical background of bombing in U.S. history, in the light of the massive Oklahoma City bombing), 28 April 1995 (Box 7)
  - U.S. Transition: Post-Cold War Problems (Weissman and Ira Sohn discuss the problems that the U.S. faces as Washington attempts to adjust to the rise of third world economic growth), 19 May 1995 (Box 7)
  - Coalescence of Radical Right Groups (Weissman interviews author Chris Phelps on the disintegration of differences among the three U.S. radical right groups, the "New Right," the Armed Right, and the Christian Right), 26 May 1995 (Box 7)
  - U.S. Iran Policy Serious Disaster (Weissman interviews Dr. Ali Jivadi, a member of the staff of the review International, published in Farsi, and on the editorial board of Socialist Workers Review. Dr. Jivadi claims that Iran is in the mood for change to more western thought and the American embargo will only support the current reactionary regime), 23 June 1995 (Box 7)
  - Economic Catastrophes Loom in World (Weissman and H. Ticktin discuss the economic and political crisis in Russia in particular as well as world-wide), 30 June 1995 (Box 7)
  - Inner History of the Cold War (Weissman and Prof. Abbot Gleason, History Department, Brown University, discuss his new book Totalitarianism - The Inner History of the Cold War, a scholarly investigation of similarities and differences, real and philosophical-political, in 20th century European history), 7 July 1995 (Box 7)
  - Serbs Continue Genocide as Powers Talk (Weissman interviews Barbara Magas on the continuing genocide by Serbs in ex-Yugoslavia while powers fail to act decisively. By telephone from London), 21 July 1995 (Box 7)
  - Bosnia: Posturing by Powers Continue (Weissman interviews Ian Williams, president of the United Nations Correspondents Assn., writer for The Nation and author of the new book UN for Beginners. The discussion centers on the continued fighting and at the same time the diplomatic stalemate as the powers posture), 28 July 1995 (Box 7)
  - U.S. Labor Loses Living STDS (James Petris, discusses the current economic situation impact on labor), 1 September 1995 (Box 7)
  - Peace Program Dims in Near East War (Michael McAdams, Regional Director of the Sacramento CA campus of the University of San Francisco discusses the complex problems of ex-Yugoslavia entities), 8 September 1995 (Box 7)
  - World Retreat of the Intellectuals (Chris Phelps, Department of History at the Simon Fraser University, Vancouver, Canada, and Weissman discuss the world-wide retreat of intellectuals in the face of class politics and capitalist action. The "new" philosophy of the late Sidney Hook is analyzed as one example), 15 September 1995 (Box 7)
  - Bosnia "Peace Plan" Likely to Fail (Melanie Lasiewicz of Convoy, Bosnia, and Arilla Hoare, PhD candidate at Yale, discuss the power-brokered "peace" plan for Bosnia with Weissman), 22 September 1995 (Box 7)
  - Labor Disarray in Russian Transition Era (Dr. Robert Arnet author of the new book, Controlling Soviet Labor (Macmillan) and Weissman discuss labor malaise during the transition process to the market), 29 September 2010 (Box 7)
  - Bosnia Air Strikes Speed Uneasy Peace (Michael McAdams, Regional Director of the Sacramento CA campus of the University of San Francisco, and Weissman discuss the continuing peace efforts in ex-Yugoslavia), 6 October 1995 (Box 7)
  - The O.J. Trial in Retrospect (Drs. Weissman and Clare Spark discuss the polarization of race lines, not based on class), 13 October 1995 (Box 7)
  - Yevtushenko-Weissman Interview (Yevgeny Yevtushenko and Weissman discuss the Russian poet's new book, Don't Die Before You Are Dead. The poet also reads some of his poems), 17 November 1995 (Box 7)
  - The Farce of Russian Elections (Professor Michael Urban, University of California at Santa Cruz, professor of politics, and Weissman, discuss the upcoming December and June elections in Russia), 1 December 1995 (Box 7)
  - Russian Election Outcome Still in Doubt (H. Ticktin, notes the complexity of the upcoming elections in Russia in an interview with Weissman), 8 December 1995 (Box 7)
  - Preview of Russian Elections (Alexander Buzgalin, Professor of Political Economy at the University of Moscow, editor of magazine Alternatives, and founder and head of "Founders of Democracy," and Weissman, in a teleconference from Moscow preview and analyze the Russian elections), 15 December 1995 (Box 7)
- 1996
  - Impact of Strikes in France and the U.S. (From "Portraits of the Soviet Union" to "Portraits of the Former Soviet Union" to "The New World Disorder" Weissman starts the first of a new series entitled "Beneath the Surface." This first program deals with strikes in France with M. Lowy, speaking from Paris, and Kim Moody, speaking from Detroit), 12 January 1996 (Box 7)
  - No Peace in Chechnia, Fragile in Bosnia (Ned Walker, Executive Director, Soviet and Post-Soviet Political Study Center at UC Berkeley, and Weissman discuss the continued volatile war in Chechnia. Atilla Hoare, a graduate student at Yale, and Weissman discuss the unstable peace in Bosnia), 19 January 1996 (Box 7)
  - Interview with Ex-neo-Nazi (Ingo Hasselbach is an ex-neo-Nazi from East Germany who, with American Tom Reiss, has written a book Führer-ex (Random House) detailing his change from a rabid neo-Nazi to an ex-neo-Nazi. Dr. Clare Spark comments on the psychological importance of the transformation), 16 February 1996 (Box 7)
  - China Becoming a U.S. Vassal? (Weissman and Dr. Ira Sohn, an expert on China and the Far East discuss the objectives of U.S. policy since the collapse of the USSR), 1 March 1996 (Box 7)
  - Russian Elections Bring New Problems (H. Ticktin, Michael Urban, and Weissman probe the complications of the upcoming Russian elections), 8 March 1996 (Box 7)
  - U.S. Global Power Breeds Domestic Ill (Weissman interviews James Petris, with an emphasis on his new book Empire or Republic: Global Power and Domestic Decay. Dr. Ira Sohn, the second guest and expert on China and the Far East, notes that U.S. policy between Taiwan and China is to "divide and rule"), 22 March 1996 (Box 7)